All right, it's about time to look at
the African-American Civil Rights
Movement straight in the dang face. And
that face is more complicated than you
might think. And I reckon we ought to
talk about it. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. Okay, for Kevin in the back of the
room who was asleep for the video on
8.6, let me just recap real quick how
the efforts of black Americans to expand
their access to civil rights in the
1960s was actually built on the
foundation of what occurred in the 1940s
and 50s. So, back then black activists
formed organizations like the Congress
of Racial Equality and the NAACP, both
of which applied different methods to
the task of securing black rights. For
example, members of CORE sponsored the
Journey of Reconciliation in which black
and white people rode public
transportation in order to challenge
segregation laws across the South. And
then NAACP lawyers like Thurgood
Marshall worked to dismantle segregation
through the courts. And the veritable
acme of that effort was the court's
decision in Brown v. Board of Education,
which overturned the separate but equal
doctrine established in the earlier
Plessy v. Ferguson case and mandated the
racial integration of schools. And look,
there's a whole lot more I could say
about the developments of that period,
but I already made a video on it and I'm
just trying to get Kevin up to speed
here. And so, really there are two major
ideas that you need to remember about
this iteration of the Civil Rights
Movement that's going to set up what
we're going to talk about in the 1960s.
First of all, many of these efforts were
rooted in the idea that promises were
made to black Americans during the
Reconstruction period, but had thus far
gone unfulfilled. And second, once the
government began making good on some of
these promises in the 40s and 50s, the
pace at which black Americans could
access those new liberties was
exceedingly slow. And so, when we get to
the 1960s, it's time to go ahead and
turn up the heat. And speaking of
additional heat, I know you can feel the
hot stinky breath of that national APUSH
exam breathing down your neck. And if
you need help getting a five on that
thing, then you might want to check out
my APUSH summer review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. And that link, my dear pupil,
is down in the description. Anyway, now
that we have the context for this topic
unlocked, let's get to the juicy bit.
And here's where I tell you that the
push for black equality in the 1960s
expanded to new issues beyond
disenfranchisement and segregation. In
other words, in this decade, the
movement expanded to include issues of
systemic inequalities in dang near every
aspect of American life. And it was a
pretty diverse movement featuring
multiple different strategies for
achieving the same end goal. And so, the
first strategy for achieving black
equality was nonviolence rooted in civil
disobedience. And both of those concepts
are important to understand. The
nonviolent bit means that while black
Americans endured violence in their
efforts to grasp their rightful claim to
constitutional liberties, they refused
to offer violence in return. And the
civil disobedience bit means that their
strategy was to intentionally break laws
in order to put on full display the
injustice of those laws to the watching
public. In fact, some American civil
rights leaders in part learned the
profound effectiveness of the strategy
by observing the nonviolent civil rights
movement in colonial India led by
Mohandas Gandhi. But there was also an
American tradition informing the civil
rights movement, and that came from the
transcendentalist Henry David Thoreau's
essay called Civil Disobedience. In that
essay, he argued that the presence of
unjust laws require Americans to follow
their consciences rather than the
corrupt legal code. Anyway, that's the
ideological foundation of the nonviolent
movements. So now, let me give you some
examples of how this played out. First
of all, the decade started with a
campaign known as the Freedom Rides,
which was sponsored by the Congress of
Racial Equality. And using the same
tactics as the CORE-sponsored Journey of
Reconciliation from the 1940s and '50s,
black activists boarded buses and trains
in the South to ensure that those states
were complying with a 1960 Supreme Court
decision that banned racial segregation
on public transportation. And although
CORE officials reached out to the FBI
and the Justice Department to let the
agencies know what they were planning,
the government made no effort to protect
the Freedom Riders. And to put it
mildly, things got nasty. For example,
when the Freedom Riders arrived in
Alabama, the Ku Klux Klan went ahead and
attacked the buses and seriously injured
several of the passengers. And as a
result, CORE decided to cancel future
Freedom Rides. But the Student
Nonviolent Coordinating Committee,
otherwise known by its sassier name
SNCC, took up the cause and continued
challenging segregation on public
transportation. And not surprisingly,
SNCC activists were also brutalized by
white mobs in Alabama as well. But that
brutality got the attention of another
civil rights activist in Atlanta, namely
Martin Luther King Jr. And so, in
response, King organized a rally in a
Montgomery church in order to encourage
the Freedom Riders to continue their
cause for black equality through
non-violence and that got the Montgomery
whites a real cranky. And so, when white
mobs threatened violence against this
gathering, which would have led to
significant bloodshed, President Kennedy
finally intervened. He sent federal
marshals to protect the gathering and
convinced the Alabama governor to
contribute to the security detail by
sending in the National Guard. And
although Kennedy had campaigned on
promises to make progress toward racial
equality, so far he hadn't done that
much on account of stiff opposition from
Congress. However, such racial violence
tarnished the reputation of the United
States in the wider context of the Cold
War and thus convinced Kennedy to move
within executive authority to remedy the
problem. Anyway, the next year King lent
his growing popularity as the de facto
leader of the non-violent civil rights
movement to another ongoing struggle in
Birmingham, Alabama. There are black
activists gathered to demonstrate
against segregation and police
brutality, but they were met with the
very brutality against which they were
protesting. The city's commissioner of
public safety, Eugene Bull Connor,
ordered the police to disperse these
protesters, some of whom were children,
with high-powered fire hoses and violent
attack dogs. well documented in
newspapers and on television and it gave
Americans a sense of the brutal lengths
that Southern white supremacists would
go to avoid obeying federal laws
prohibiting discrimination. And it was
also during this demonstration that
Martin Luther King Jr. was arrested and
penned one of the most enduring
ideological foundations for the
non-violent wing of the civil rights
movement, namely his letter from a
Birmingham jail. In it, he called on
black Americans to continue their
struggle for freedom by means of
non-violence. And he also dismantled the
argument that came from white
sympathizers of the black civil rights
movement, which said that black people
just need to be patient white friends
work through official channels to make
good on the promises of reconstruction.
And in essence, King said that only
those who have never been under the
persistent lash of racial discrimination
can say with a straight face, "Just
wait." Anyway, in spite of the enormous
pressure this movement put on the
government to respond, by 1963 federal
officials had still been dragging their
feet. And therefore, a coalition of
civil rights organizations organized the
March on Washington in which about a
quarter million protesters assembled
peacefully on the lawn in front of the
Lincoln Memorial and demanded that the
promises of racial equality be at last
honored. And it was during this
gathering that King delivered his I Have
a Dream speech in which he warned
government officials that the movement
for black equality would not quit until
they had achieved their goal. And by the
election of 1964, this movement became
more overtly political in an effort to
make good on those desires. For example,
black activist Fannie Lou Hamer and some
others founded the Freedom Democratic
Party which focused much of its efforts
on securing black voting rights. And
that work would later pay off with the
passage of the Voting Rights Act in
1965, of which more later. Okay, so now
that you have a taste of the non-violent
iteration of the black civil rights
movement, now I need to tell you about
the other major strategy, namely the
black power movement, and I'll give you
two examples that illustrate this
equally diverse movement. First of all,
you had Malcolm X who rejected the
strategy of non-violence in favor of
self-defense and militarism. You see, in
his opinion, non-violence was only a
viable strategy for change if the
opposition, namely white supremacists,
were also committed to non-violence. And
if that was true, then it would be a
battle of ideas and the best idea would
win. But Malcolm pointed out what was
obvious, namely that white supremacists
weren't exactly lining up to get into
the non-violence party. But in fact,
there were plenty of examples of white
on black violence during the 1960s. And
so Malcolm X gathered a following
devoted to achieving equality by
claiming black power and encouraging
black people to embrace the glories of
their African heritage. And then in
1966, Huey P. Newton and Bobby Seale
channeled a similar commitment to black
nationalism into the formation of the
Black Panther Party. So they also
endorsed violence and self-defense
against white aggression and were big
believers in the Second Amendment, which
is why you almost never see them
demonstrating without a fistful of guns.
However, I should also mention that the
Black Panthers, despite their imposing
and fearful appearance, also organized
social programs that aimed to alleviate
problems faced by impoverished black
communities in inner cities, things like
daycare for children. Regardless, the
arguments of folks like Malcolm X and
the Black Panthers began to become more
persuasive after the assassination of
Martin Luther King in 1968. After
hearing about it, the Black Panther
leader Huey Newton used King's murder as
definitive proof that non-violence and
civil disobedience could never work to
deliver black people the rights that
they had been denied. And as a result,
massive and violent race riots broke out
in big cities across the country. Okay,
now let's finish by considering how the
government responded to these various
calls for black civil rights. And I'll
give you two pieces of legislation and
two Supreme Court cases. So, the first
piece of legislation passed was the
Civil Rights Act of 1964, which
prohibited discrimination in public
facilities and employment, while also
giving the federal government authority
to oversee compliance with the law,
especially in the South. However, even
though the law contained a provision
meant to protect the right of black
Americans to vote, it really didn't
eliminate the main mechanisms that
states used to disenfranchise black
voters, things like poll taxes and
literacy tests. Therefore, on the heels
of the victory gained in the Civil
Rights Act, civil rights organizations
banded together to address voting rights
in a campaign known as the Freedom
Summer. They focused their efforts in
Mississippi and recruited something like
800 volunteers to run voter registration
drives and improve the quality of
education for black youth. And their
efforts, combined with continued
violence against black demonstrators in
Selma, Alabama, led to the passage of
the Voting Rights Act of 1965, which
addressed many of the problems
associated with the disenfranchisement
of black voters. But then, the Civil
Rights Movement also scored several
important victories in the Supreme
Court. So, as I mentioned in a previous
video, although the court had
illegalized school segregation in Brown
v. Board of Education, the actual
implementation of school integration had
been painfully slow as government
officials at the state and city levels
made every effort to prevent it.
Therefore, the court ruled in 1969 that
school integration must occur
immediately. And then, 2 years later,
the court provided the mechanism through
which such speedy integration could
occur. In the case Swann v. the
Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of
Education, the court mandated that
integration occur by means of school
bussing programs. In other words, white
and black students were now required to
be bussed to other schools in order to
increase the ratio of white to black
students. And in some states, the
mandate had the intended effect, but
other states, you should not be
surprised by now, resisted the
integration order. For example, parents
in Detroit, Michigan, complained loudly
that they should not have to send their
children into another school district in
order to cooperate with integration
orders. And so, in 1973, the court ruled
in favor of these parents, and that
decision removed much of the efficacy of
federally mandated school integration.
And then, the second major decision came
in Loving v. Virginia in 1967, which
declared state laws against interracial
marriage to be unconstitutional. But
even with these kinds of victories
enshrined in the code of law, the fight
for black civil rights will continue up
to the present day. And yet, the limited
success of the movement actually
inspired other marginalized groups to
organize their own civil rights
movements, but that's the story for the
next video. Okay, you can click here to
watch my other Unit 8 videos or you can
click here to grab my APUSH Heimler
Review Guide which has everything you
need to study as fast as possible. I'm
glad you came around and I'll catch you
on the flip flop. Heimler out.